RG 036, Temporary State Housing Rent Commission
Connecticut State Library
Temorary State Housing Rent Commission records
1942-1956
bulk 1952-1955
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Temorary State Housing Rent Commission
5 cubic feet
During the Second World War, national rent controls began under the Office of Price Administration-directed offices. In 1947, anticipating the end of national controls, the Connecticut General Assembly enacted a series of standby rent control laws. One of these, Chapter 356 of the 1951 Supplement to the General Statutes, created the Temporary State Housing Rent Commission.
RG036
T002690
Historical Note
Like other prices during World War II, housing rents were limited and policed through Federal Government agencies, the Office of Price Administration and its predecessors. Rent controls began in Connecticut in June and July 1942 under the Office of Price Administration-directed area offices, and these offices continued after the war ended, as local arms of new Federal agencies - the Office of the Housing Expediter, the Office of Rent Stabilization, etc. Even at the end of 1952, Federal control extended over 48 "critical area" towns and 39 other towns which requested it.
In anticipation of the expiration of United States authority, the General Assembly enacted a series of standby rent control laws beginning in 1947. Under one of these, Chapter 356 of the 1951 Supplement to the General Statutes, the Governor set up Temporary State Housing Rent Commission. Beginning on October 1, 1952, it was to work at first primarily in the 82 towns where Federal controls no longer existed. The first commissioner, James T. Sullivan, and his successor in 1953, James L. Delucia, had both been officials (and Director) of the Area Rent Control Office in Hartford. The Temporary Commission appears to have ended its work on April 1, 1956.
Scope and Content
The record group contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, instructions, hand written notes, minutes of meetings and agendas, rent surveys, subject files, rent case docket registers, and statistical analyses and working papers concerning demographics and housing and rental units in Connecticut. It also includes federal manuals, bulletins, circulars, files of the Hartford Area Rent Office (1942-1953), and papers of an attorney who handled questions of compliance with U. S. regulations giving preference in housing to veterans.
Related Material
RG 005, Office of the Governor, records of various governors under relevant headings ("housing", "rent control", "Temporary Rent Commission", etc.)
RG 035, Office of Price Administration, Connecticut, 1942-1949
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Temporary State Housing Rent Commission
Subjects:
Connecticut. Temporary State Housing Rent Commission -- Records and correspondence; Rental housing -- Connecticut; Rent control -- Connecticut; Rent -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Circulars (fliers); Correspondence; Memorandums; Notes; Newsletters; Registers; Surveys (documents)
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
After the Temporary Commission ended its work on April 1, 1956, the records were presumably turned over to the State Library soon thereafter, but substantial parts may have been lost or destroyed.
Container List
- Records, 1942-1956
  - 1. General file, 1952-1955
    Contains correspondence, memoranda, instructions, reports, notes, etc.
    Grouped by subject.
    - General (correspondence) (Box 1)
      Arranged in chronological order.
    - Miscellaneous (administrative matters, personnel) (Box 1)
    - Officials (town officials, Congress, General Assembly) (Box 1)
    - Publications (reference materials) (Box 1)
    - Rent Board (minutes, agenda, correspondence) (Box 1)
    - Rent Commission (orders, regulations, procedures, blank forms) (Box 1-2)
    - Rent Offices (Connecticut and elsewhere) (Box 2)
    - Requests (Box 2)
    - State Departments (including annual reports to the Governor) (Box 2)
    - Survey (replies to inquiry) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous and unfiled material (Box 2)
      Some labelled by subject.
  - 2. Docket registers, 1951-1956 (Box 3)
    Contains form lists of cases received and handled.
    Grouped by type of case.
  - 3. Statistical analyses and working papers, 1952-1955 (Box 3-4)
    Contains analyses of population, housing and rental units in Connecticut towns, with related working papers, notes and reference materials.
    Unarranged.
  - 4. Manuals and instructions, 1942-1955 (Box 4)
    Contains printed and mimeographed copies of statutes, manuals, bulletins, circulars and memoranda of instructions from various Federal agencies (Office of Price Administration, Housing Expediter, Rent Stabilization, etc.)
  - 5. Files of the Area Rent Office, Hartford, 1942-1953 (Box 5)
    Contains correspondence, memoranda and reports.
    Grouped by subject or correspondent.
  - 6. Veterans preference files, 1947-1949 (Box 5)
    Contains papers of Robert F. Crary, attorney, who dealt with questions of compliance with U. S. regulations giving housing preference to veterans. Mostly instructions and procedural memoranda.